Chaitanya Kapoor

□ chaitanya.7.kapoor@gmail.com

github.com/ckapoor7

□ ckapoor7.github.io

(Nationality: Citizen of the United States of America)

Research Interests

My research interests lie at the intersection of Deep Learning and Neuroscience, aiming to understand and reverse engineer neural computation. I aim to develop computational models of cognitive neural circuits, with an overarching goal of designing efficient, biologically-constrained learning algorithms.

Education

University of California, San Diego

Aug. 2024 – Present

Post-Baccalaureate Student (NeuroML Group)

La Jolla, CA

Advisor: Meenakshi Khosla

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Jan. 2024 - July 2024

Visiting Student (Senseable Intelligence Group)

Cambridge, MA

Thesis: LUMIN: Light-sheet Microscopy Analysis Unified with Distributed and Domain-Randomized

Generative Models

Advisor: Satrajit Ghosh

Birla Institute of Technology and Science, Pilani

B.E. (Hons.) in Electrical and Electronics engineering

Nov. 2020 - July 2024

Pilani, India

Honors & Awards

04/24 NeuroMatch Academy: Computational Neuroscience Summer School

02/24 COSYNE 2024: Undergraduate Travel Grant Award

04/23 OxML 2023: ML × Health Summer School, Oxford Mathematical Institute

Publications

Multiplexed Expansion Revealing for Imaging Multiprotein Nanostructures in Healthy and Diseased Brain

J. Kang, M. Schroeder, Y. Lee, C. Kapoor, E. Yu, T. B. Tarr, K. Titterton, M. Zeng, D. Park, E. Niederst, D. Wei, E. S. Boyden

Nature Communications, 2024 - code

RnR-ExM: Robust Non-Rigid Registration Challenge for Expansion Microscopy Volumes

E. Besier, R. Zhang, Y. Bando, Y. Quéméner, C. Kapoor, M. Alawi, M. Hoffman, A. Dalca, A.

Casamitjana, I. Arganda-Carreras, E. S. Boyden, H. Pfister, D. Wei

IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (IEEE ISBI), 2023 - website

Attention-enabled Deep Neural Network for Enhancing UAV-Captured Pavement Imagery in Poor Visibility

C. Kapoor, A. Warrier, M. Singh, P. Narang, H. Puppala, R. Srinivas, A. P. Singh IEEE Multimedia Information Processing and Retrieval (IEEE MIPR), 2023 - paper

Fast and Lightweight UAV-based Road Image Enhancement Under Multiple Low-Visibility Conditions

C. Kapoor, A. Warrier, M. Singh, P. Narang, H. Puppala, R. Srinivas, A. P. Singh PerCom Workshops (PerSASN 2023) - paper

Dense Residual Networks for Gaze Mapping on Indian Roads

C. Kapoor, K. Kumar, S. Vishnoi, S. Ramanathan preprint

Research Experience

NeuroML Lab Aug. 2024 – Present

Supervisor: Prof. Meenakshi Khosla

La Jolla, CA

• Working on developing methods to quantify representational similarity in artificial and biological neural networks.

Talmo Lab May 2023 – Aug. 2024

Supervisor: Dr. Talmo Pereira

Salk Institute, La Jolla, CA

- Worked on the development of methods for pose estimation and tracking to quantify animal behavior through robust tracking of anatomical landmarks in 3D.
- Designed algorithms utilizing projective geometry to create inputs for a CNN that leverages geometric reasoning.

Senseable Intelligence Group

Jan. 2024 - July 2024

Supervisor: Prof. Satrajit Ghosh

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MA

- Developed a distributed framework for large-scale (\approx 1TiB) image segmentation for light-sheet microscopy images.
- Designed a domain-randomized generative model, using spherical harmonics to synthesize cortical sections of ex-vivo human brains to enable zero-shot segmentation.
- Worked on designing few-shot, spatially guided semantic segmentation algorithms for MRI segmentation.
- Proposed the use of a topologically aware Graph Neural Network which is capable of encoding spatial and anatomical constraints.

Synthetic Neurobiology Group

Feb. 2022 - Jan. 2024

Supervisors: Prof. Ed Boyden, Prof. Donglai Wei

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MA

- Worked on the development of a *generalist* 3D segmentation model for Expansion Microscopy (ExM) volumes for various animal species.
- Proposed a human-in-the-loop feedback learning mechanism, built on top of an existing deep learning framework, NucMM.
- Worked on developing a new joint-intensity and point-based, high throughput image registration algorithms having nanoscale precision (10 40 nm) for Multiplexed Expansion Revealing (multiExR). This work has been published at Nature Communications.

Invited Talks and Tutorials

02/24 Automating behavior quantification using deep learning, COSYNE 2024

06/23 SIS Symposium, Harvard SEAS, Seeing Beyond the Camera

Teaching Experience

Department of Mathematics, BITS Pilani

August 2023 - Dec. 2023

Teaching Assistant

Pilani, India

• Undergraduate TA: assisted with the course Combinatorial Mathematics (MATH F421)

Technical Skills

Languages: Python, C, MATLAB, Unix Shell Scripting, LATEX

Technologies/Frameworks: Keras, Tensorflow, Numpy, PyTorch, Git, OpenCV